here's a right triangle and let's label
the legs A and B in the hypotenuse C we
can draw and shade an a by a square off
the a leg and we can draw and shade a b
by b square off the B leg like this we
can also draw but leave unshaded a c by
C Square Off the hypotenuse so the
unshaded area in this diagram is given
by c squared but now we're going to
shift and rotate objects around this
shape to produce a different unshaded
area first we use the triangle to
decompose the B by b square into two
pieces like this then we rotate the
original triangle down 90 degrees shift
the original a by a square like this and
then we shift and rotate and then break
along the hinge the original B by b
square filling the diagram now we see
that the unshaded area is given by a
squared plus b squared this means that
in a right triangle with legs of length
A and B and hypotenuse c c squared
equals a squared plus b squared this is
the Pythagorean theorem